<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to bee enquired of by the minister, church-wardens, and sidemen of euery parish and chapelry within the deanry of [blank] in the yeare of our Lord God [blank] and presentment to be made by them conteining a particular answer to euery article</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10147.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22884117</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22884117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25856</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00153)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1777:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to bee enquired of by the minister, church-wardens, and sidemen of euery parish and chapelry within the deanry of [blank] in the yeare of our Lord God [blank] and presentment to be made by them conteining a particular answer to euery article</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10333.--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Blank deanery forms for the province of Canterbury."--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: creased and torn with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Marsh's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="agenda">
            <pb facs="tcp:25856:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Articles to bee enquired of by the Miniſter, Church-wardens, and Sidemen of euery
Pariſh and Chapelry within the Deanry of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the yeare of our Lord God <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> And preſentment to be
made by them conteining a particular Anſwer to euery Article.</head>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>The forme of the OATH taken by the Church-wardens and Sidemen.</head>
               <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that you and euery of you ſhall dulie conſider and diligently informe your ſelues of theſe Articles giuen you in charge, and that all
fauour, hatred, hope, feare, or any other corrupt affection ſet aſide, you ſhall preſent all and euery ſuch perſon now or lately of your Pariſh, which
haue committed any offence comprized in any of theſe Articles, or which ar<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vehemently ſuſpected or defamed of any ſuch offence. Wherein you
ſhall deale according to an vpright conſcience, neither preſenting nor ſparing t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſent any perſon contrary to truth, So helpe you God, and his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
promiſes in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HETHER haue you in your Church all things requiſite for the common Prayer,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>rch.</note> and due adminiſtration of the Sacraments?<note place="margin">Canon.</note> And namely a faire Bible, the
Booke of common Prayer,<note place="margin">80. 81. 82. 83. 84, 70.</note> lately ordeined only to be vſed? A Font of ſto<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſet vp in the ancient vſuall place? A decent Communion table ſtanding vpon a frame,
with a carpet of ſilke or ſome other ſeemely ſtuffe, and a faire linnen clot<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to lay thereon at the time of communion? A faire communion Cup with a couer of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer:
a decent Pulpit with a cloth and Cuſhion for the ſame: a conueni<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t ſeat to read ſeruice in: a comely large ſurplice: a ſtrong cheſt for almes for the poore
with three lockes and keyes, and another cheſt for keeping the Ornaments of the Church and Regiſter booke: and whether haue you a Regiſter booke in parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of all Chriſtnings, Weddings, and Burials: and whether is the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ept according to the Canons, and a tranſcript thereof brought yeerely into the Office
of principall Regiſtrie of the L. Archb. of <hi>Canterbury?</hi> And whether <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſter vpon euery Sunday reade the names of ſuch as haue beene chriſtened,
married, or buried in the weeke before?</p>
               <p>2 Whether your Church,<note place="margin">85. 88.</note> Chancell and Churchyard be kept in good reparation <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> without: whether any prophanation be or hath beene vſed in them: or whether
any man hath incroached vpon them: And whether your perſonage or vicaridge <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereunto belonging, be likewiſe maintained in ſufficient reparations: If not,
through whoſe default, and what is the defect?</p>
               <p>3 Whether haue you a Terrier of all the gleabe Landes,<note place="margin">87.</note> Meadowes, Gardens, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>des, Houſes, Stockes, Implements, Tenements, and portions of Tythes lying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
or without your Pariſh which belong to your Parſonage or Vicaridge, and in whoſe ha<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>oeth it remaine: If not, you ſhall together with your Miniſter make diligent enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
of all the premiſes, and exhibite with your next preſentment a true note of them in <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ent ſubſcribed with your hands, ſpecifying how they are buttalled or bounded, and in
whoſe occupation at this preſent they are?</p>
               <p>4 VVHether diuine ſeruice be ſaid in your Church by your Miniſter diſtinctly and re<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erently,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> vpon Sundayes and ſuch holydaies as are appointed to be obſerued by the book
of Common prayer,<note place="margin">14. 15. 58.</note> and their Eues, and vpon Wedneſdaies and Fridaies at emuenient and vſuall times: and whether doth he in miniſtring the Sacraments, ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
of matrimony, viſitation of the ſicke, burying the dead, churching of women, or any other rites and offices of the Church, vſe the formes of prayers preſcribed in
the ſame booke, without any omiſſion or addition: And whether doth he read the booke of Canons once yeerely, and weare a Surplice according to the Canon?</p>
               <p>5 Whether doth your Miniſter ſolemnly giue warning to his Pariſhioners for the holy Communion,<note place="margin">22. 64. 67. 84. 66. 26. 27. 28. 29. 62. 63. 68. 69. 62. 100.</note> and for all Holydaies &amp; faſting daies? And whether doth hee viſite the ſick when
he is thereunto deſired to comfort and inſtruct them? And whether doth hee offer to confere with Recuſants in your Pariſh if there bee any? And whether doth hee admit to the
holy Communion any notorious offenders, ſchiſmatickes, or ſtrangers of other Pariſhes; or r<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iect any, who are not by preſentment or publique ſcandall infamous for ſome notorious
crime? And whether doth he admit any Father to be Godfather to his owne Childe; or any to be Godfathers and Godmothers which haue not receiued the holy Communion? or
doth not vſe the ſigne of the Croſſe in baptiſme? or doth baptize in any baſon or other veſſell, and not in the vſuall Font? or doth baptize any children that were not borne within the
Pariſh? And whether doth he marry any in any exempt place, or without banes publiſhed three, ſeuerall Sundaies or Holidaies, or without a ſufficient diſpenſation or licence, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
licence in times prohibited, albeit the banes were thrice publiſhed, or not betwixt the houres of 8. and 12. in the forenoone, or if the parties bee vnder the age of 21. yeares, before
their parents haue ſignified their conſent vnto him? or whether doth hee refuſe to Chriſten, or to bury, or doth deferre the ſame longer then hee ſhould? and whether by his default any
Childe hath died without baptiſme in your Pariſh?</p>
               <p>6 Whether doth he preach, miniſter the communion, baptize children,<note place="margin">70. 71. 72. 73. 74.</note> or church women (vnleſſe in caſe of neceſſitie) or in any caſe without a faculty ſolemnize matrimony in
priuate houſes? Or doth keepe or ſuffer any Faſtes, Propheſies, Exerciſes, or Exorciſmes without lawfull authoritie; or doth hold or ſuffer any priuate conuenticles? And whether doth
he frequent Tauernes: Alchouſes, or any place ſuſpected for incontinencie, or doth table or ledge in any ſuch houſe? or is hee a common gameſter at Dice, Cardes, Tables, or any
other vnlawfull game; a Swearer or Drunkard, or one that applieth not himſelfe to his ſtudi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Or doth not vſe decencie in his apparrell? Or is otherwiſe offenſiue or ſcandalous
to his function and miniſtry?</p>
               <p>7 Whether is hee continually reſident vpon his benefice,<note place="margin">45, 46. 47. 74.</note> and how longtime hath hee beene abſent from the ſame? (in caſe hee belicenced to be abſent) whether doth he cauſe his
cure to be ſufficiently ſupplied? And whether (if hee bee allowed a Preacher) doth hee preach one Sermon euery Sunday? or (if not ſo allowed) doth procure monthly ſermons, and
read Homilies? And whether (not being ſo allowed) doth hee expound any Scripture, or ſuffer any man to preach in your Church, whom you haue not well knowne, to haue beene
ſufficiently licenced, and who hath not firſt ſubſcribed his name, together with the day when he did preach, and who was not ſoberly and decently apparrelled?</p>
               <p>8 Whether doth your Preacher and Lecturer read diuine ſeruice,<note place="margin">56. 55.</note> and miniſter the Sacraments twice a yeare at the leaſt, in his owne perſon? And whether doth hee vſe the forme
of prayer before his ſermons for the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, exhorting the people to obedience to his Maieſtie, and other Magiſtrates in authority vnder him?</p>
               <p>9 Whether doth your Miniſter on Sundaies and Holidaies Catechize the Youth and ignorant perſons in your Pariſh?<note place="margin">59.</note> And whether doth hee admit any women to bee churched
who were begotten with childe in adultery or fornication, without licence from the Ordinarie And whether doth hee in the Rogation dayes vſe the perambulation of the circuite of
the Pariſh?</p>
               <p>10 Whether doth he euery ſixe moneths denounce in his Pariſh Church all ſuch o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>riſh as doe perſeuer in the ſentence of excommunication, not ſeeking to bee abſolued?
And whether hath hee admitted any ſuch excommunicate perſon to the communion, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church without certificate of his abſolution? And whether doth hee or any of your
Pariſh familiarly frequent the company of any ſuch excommunicate perſon?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>11 WHether any of your Pariſhioners doe not cauſe their <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>rs.</note>and Apprenti<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, to come to <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon Sundaies and Holidaies to bee inſtructed
in the Catechiſme by them?<note place="margin">59.</note> or whether any of them refuſe to come? or if they come, refuſe to be inſtructed? And what bee the names of them ſo not cauſing, or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing?</p>
               <p>12 Whether any of your Pariſhioners,<note place="margin">13. 14. 18.</note> or other ſtrangers ſoiourning, lodging, or commonly reſorting to any houſe within your Pariſh, aboue 16. yeares of age, doe wilfully or
negligently abſent themſelues from your pariſh Church, vpon Sundayes or Holidayes at Morning or Euening prayer? or who come very late to Church vpon the ſaid dayes? or who
depart from Church before ſeruice bee finiſhed? or who doe not reuerently behaue themſelues during the time of diuine Seruice, deuoutly kneeling at ſuch times as the generall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
of ſinnes, the Letanie, the ten Commandements, and all prayers and Collects are read? or who doe vſe any gameing or paſtime abroad, or in any houſe, or doe ſit in the ſtreet,
or Church-yard, or in any Tauerne, or Victualing-houſe vpon any of thoſe dayes in time of diuine Seruice? or who haue quarrelled, brawled, or vſed violence to any perſon within
your Church, or Church-yard? or who hath vſed filthy or prophane talke, or other rude and in modeſt behauiour there?</p>
               <p>13 Whether there be any of,<note place="margin">21. 22, 28.</note> or within your pariſh being ſixteene yeeres of age, and vpwards, that doe not receiue the holy Communion in your Church thrice in this yeare at the
leaſt, and chiefly once at Eaſter? And whether any of your pariſh doth not deuoutly kneele at the receiuing thereof? And whether doth not your Miniſter receiue it himſelfe on euery
day that he adminiſtreth it to others, and vſe the words of inſtitution at euery time that the bread and wine is adminiſtred? And whether doe your ſelues diligently obſerue your office,
in marking what perſons of or within your pariſh offend againſt this, or the next precedent Article, and in due preſenting their names?</p>
               <p>14 Whether any in your pariſh haue a Preacher to your Parſon,<note place="margin">46. 10. 57. 9. 10. 100.</note> Vicar, or Curate, doe abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to other places to heare other Preacher?
And whether any hauing beene ordeyned Prieſt, or Deacon, hath relinquiſhed the ſame, and be <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>en him to a courſe of life as a lay man? Or whether any not being in Orders, doth
openly read Common prayer, or execute any miniſteriall dutie in your Church, and what be their names?</p>
               <p>15 Whether there be any that doe publiquely or priuately ſpeake againſt the Booke of Common prayer, deprauing the ſame or any thing therein contained? or againſt any of the
ſaid Articles of Religion agreed vpon in. <hi>Anno</hi> 1562? Or againſt the Kings Royall Supremacie i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> cauſes Eccleſiaſticall? Or againſt any of the rites or ceremonies of the Church of
<hi>England?</hi> Or againſt the gouernment of the ſaid Church of <hi>England</hi> vnder the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, by Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, &amp; other Officers in the
ſame, affirming, that the ſame is repugnant to the word of God, and that the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall Officers are not lawfully ordeyned? Or whether there by any that be Authors or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers
of Sciſme, or frequenters of any priuate conuenticles or meetings? or that be, or are ſuſpected to be Anabaptiſts, Libertines, Browniſts, of the Familie of Loue, other herefie
orſchiſme, And what be their names?</p>
               <p>16 Whether doe you know any Schoolemaſter that doth teach,<note place="margin">77. 48. 79.</note> or Curate that doth reade diuine Seruice within your pariſh, without licence of his Ordinary vnder his Scale? And
whether doth not ſuch Schoolemaſter inſtruct his ſchollers in the Catechiſme, and teach them he grounds of Religion, and bring them to Church to heare diuine Seruice and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons?
And whether is he a common officer or artificer, or any wayes reprooueable in life? And whether is your Clarke alſo allowed by the Ordinary? And whether doth your clarke
ſerue more cures than one? And whether doe they demeane themſelues according to their ſe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rall duties?</p>
               <p>17 How many Midwiues haue you in your Pariſh which doe exerciſe that office? how long <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue they ſo done, and by what authoritie? Alſo how many in your Pariſh doe practiſe
as Phyſitions or Chirurgions? how long haue they ſo done, and of what skill are they reputed their profeſſion?</p>
               <p>18 Whether doe you know any perſons that doe adminiſter the goods of the dead without la<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full authoritie?<note place="margin">86.</note> or ſuppreſſe the laſt will of the dead? or with-hold any ſtocke of the
Church, or any Legacies giuen to godly and charitable vſes? and whether is the almes of the Church faithfully diſtributed to the vſe of the poore? And whether the late Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
haue giuen a iuſt accompt before the Miniſter and Pariſhoners at the end of their yeere, according to the Canon?</p>
               <p>19 Whether doe you know in your pariſh any common ſwearers, drunkards, blaſphemers, any <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oniacal perſons, or vſuerers contrary to the Statute 37. of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, any ſooth-ſayers,
charmers, fornicators, adulterers, inceſtious perſons, brawlers, common ſlanderers of the neighbours, raylers, ſcoulds, ſilthy and laſciuious talkers, ſowers of diſcord between
neighbors, or any that receiue or lodge incontinent perſons, or harbour women with childe whi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> be vnmarried, conueying or ſuffering them to goe away before they haue made ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction
to the congregation? or any perſons that are by common fame noted or vehemently <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ected of any of theſe crimes? or that being heretofore ſuſpected, or preſented for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of theſe faults, haue for that cauſe departed out of your Pariſh, and are now returned againe?</p>
               <p>20 Whether there bee any perſons within your Pariſh that be married within the prohibited <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>grees of conſanguinitie or affininitie, or their old wiues or huſbands being yet aliue,
albeit diuorced from them;<note place="margin">99. 57.</note> or that being lawfully married, doe liue ſcandalouſly apart, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> married in times prohibited, or without banes three ſeuerall Sundayes or Holy-daies
publiſhed, hauing no ſufficient licence or diſpenſation for the ſame? And whether there <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ar doe communicate, or cauſe their children to be baptized in other Pariſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,
or keepe their children vnbaptized longer then is conuenient?</p>
               <p>21 Whether any woman deliured of childe in your Pariſh, in time conuenient after child-b<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th, doe not come to the vſuall place in the Church to giue God thanks? And whether
doth your Clarke lap a Cuſhion at the ſaid vſuall place?<note place="margin">117.</note> whether any inhabitant within your Pariſh doth detaine the Clarkes wages, dueties for bread and wine, or any other Church
dueties? preſent particularly what be their names, and what and how much thoſe dueties be?</p>
               <p>22 Whether any perſon in your Pariſh doe exerciſe any Trade, Handicraft, or bodily labour or doe buy and ſell, or keepe open Shops or warehouſes vpon any Sunday or Holiday,
by themſelues, their ſeruants or Apprentizes, or haue otherwiſe prophaned the ſayd daies contrary to the order of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> And whether there bee any Inne-keepers,
Alehouſe-keepers, or Victualers, that permit any perſons in their houſes to eat, drinke, or play at any games during the time of diuine Seruice, or Sermon in the forenoone or afternoone
vpon thoſe dayes?</p>
               <p>23 Whether doe any in your Pariſh familiarly frequent the company of excommunicate perſons? And whether doeth your Miniſter or any of your Pariſh without conſent of the
Ordinarie, cauſe any to doe penance, or to be cenſured or puniſhed by any Veſtry meetings, or otherwiſe by their owne anthoritie, or doe, or haue taken any money for any crime or
matter puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall Law? who haue beene ſo puniſhed? in what manner? an<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> vpon what cauſe?</p>
               <p>24 If any one or more of you doe know,<note place="margin">113.</note> or haue heard of any fault inquired of in theſe Articles or of any other crime, the reformation whereof belongeth to the ſpirituall iuriſdict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
happening from the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> that then you doe informe one another thereof, and you ſhall likewiſe preſent the ſame by vertue of your oathes?</p>
               <p>25 The Miniſter of euery Pariſh may ioyne in euery preſentment with the Churchwardens and Sidemen,<note place="margin">118. 118.</note> who if they will not preſent, the Miniſter may himſelfe preſent to the ſaid
Commiſſary or his Surrogat ſuch faults or crimes aboueſaid, as ſhall be thought to require due reformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charge">
               <p>You are charged to ſpecifie the fault or crime, proper name and ſurname, trade or addition, and place of dwelling of euery perſon preſented. And to bring your firſt generall preſentment vpon all theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
into Bowe Church in Cheapeſide in the forenoone between the houres of viij. and xi. of the clocks, the 28. day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> next comming. And your laſt generall preſentment on the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>
day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> then next following, or elſe they and there to appeare perſonally, to ſhew the cauſe of your default therein. Intimating further, that you may (beſides thoſe generall dayes.) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
offenders, as oft as you ſhall thinke meete, as by the Canonis preſcribed, Vnto the ſayd Deane, Commiſſary, or his deputy, ſitting at any time in the open court.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
